Abraham: So, what exactly is
social engineering and why do
cyber criminals like to use it?
Social engineering is the name given
to techniques used by cyber criminals
to manipulate and trick people into
giving out confidential information,
transferring money or downloading malware.
Nicole: Social engineers use
psychology to manipulate a
victim’s feelings of curiosity
or fear to draw them into a trap.
They often find it is easier to exploit
a person’s willingness to trust rather
than go to the trouble of trying to
discover ways to hack their software.
As technology and subsequently cyber
security gets more advanced, cyber
criminals are now turning more to social
engineering, to make their initial attack
on a system by exploiting the weakest
link in an organisational chain the user.
Abraham: Unlike cyber attacks that
rely on system vulnerabilities to gain
access to unauthorised devices, social
engineering targets human vulnerabilities.
They can use a variety of methods
both online and offline such as phone
calls, emails, text messages or other
means to con unsuspecting users into
compromising their own systems or
their work-based systems by installing
malware and handing over access to their
sensitive and personal information and
potentially that of their employer.
Nicole: We have already looked at
OSINT or open source intelligence
information in previous videos but
let’s have a quick recap and look at
how open source information can help
cyber criminals with social engineering.
Abraham: Open-source information
is information that is publicly
available, and anyone can obtain by
request, purchase or observation.
Information to be considered open source
can be published or broadcast for a
public audience, available to the public
by request, subscription or purchase.
It can also be seen or heard
casually or made available at a
public meeting or by visiting a
place or event open to the public.
Nicole: Cyber criminals can use
open-source intelligence to identify
weaknesses to exploit in networks such
as accidental leaks of information
through social media, open ports or
unsecured internet connected devices.
Cyber criminals can also access
publicly available information
through social media sites.
Just think about all that information
people put online, ages, addresses,
email addresses, family and pet names,
what they are doing, where they go, what
they believe in, what they have bought.
The list is endless and gives plenty
of information to cyber criminals.
That's just a small portion of
the information that is available.
Abraham: Think about all the
other information that can
be obtained via the internet.
So how do cyber criminals use the
information they have obtained
by open source intelligence
and what do they do with it?
Nicole: Social engineering is a way
of manipulating people into breaking
their normal security protocols.
The cyber criminal uses these tactics to
exploit an individual’s trust so that they
can hack into their systems and software.
Abraham: So how can they do this
and how does this affect us?
Nicole: By using OSINT, cyber criminals
can make their attacks look legitimate,
they do this by lowering your defences.
They check out your details on social
media and have a back story prepared.
Abraham: Cyber criminals will build
an image of who they are pretending
to be, so they can talk confidently
about it and make you feel for them
to increase your sense of familiarity.
They make you more likely to do what
they want, such as click a link.
This is called pretexting.
They may, for example, research Instagram
and see that you have a pet dog and when
they make contact, could talk about how
they’ve been working at the dog shelter.
This will build an emotional
connection and establish themselves
as a good and trustworthy person.
Nicole: So what useful information can
be gained through social engineering?
Cybercriminals through social
engineering use multiple tactics to
gain information such as passwords,
usernames and banking details.
They create websites which look
legitimate using trademarks and logos.
They rely on an individual’s
trust that it must be 'legit'.
By accessing one person’s email
password they also have access to
all their contacts and many people
use the same password so they may
have access to their social media
and all their social media contacts.
Think of all those emails about winning
money or prizes, be eligible for a tax
refund, helping someone out abroad by
accepting their money into your account.
They are all ways social
engineering takes place so just
think have you ever been a victim.
Abraham: As well as traditional
social engineering where the
attacker contacts the victim.
There is also another tactic
called reverse social engineering.
In reverse social engineering the cyber
criminal will use OSINT to manipulate
a victim into contacting them.
Nicole: This could first start with
a phishing link which invites the
victim to respond, maybe they want
to upgrade their energy supply,
or have a parcel redelivered.
If they click on the link and put
in their details, they are hooked.
Abraham: The attackers also use
‘domain squatting’ which involves
setting up a fake website that
resemble one the victim uses regularly
but with a slightly different name.
They wait for the victim to
misspell the web address and click
on the familiar looking link and
add their username and password.
When they submit, they are redirected
to the legitimate site and never know
they have had their details stolen.
Nicole: Other forms of reverse social
engineering involve posting repeatedly
on a victim’s social media site until
the victim becomes curious and visits the
bogus site, therefore the link is made.
So how can social engineering
attacks be prevented?
Abraham: Threat actors will always be able
to find a way to exploit the vulnerability
of users but if the appropriate cyber
security measures are in place and
people are educated and informed about
potential threat of attacks through social
engineering the incidence may reduce.
Nicole: We all must remember to be more
vigilant in everything we do especially
online, not randomly put information
out there to be exploited, learn to
not trust so readily, and think more
carefully about what we click on, we might
lessen our chances of becoming a victim.